Guide to the Pierce Family Papers 1725-1974 MS 025 MS 025 MS 025
Cornwall Historical Society
Pierce Family Papers
1725-1974
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 025
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
The papers consist of materials relating to three generations of the Pierce family of Cornwall, principally Joshua Pierce (ca.1702-1794) and his son Seth Pierce (1742-1833), but also several of Joshua’s grandchildren.
Provenance
unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The papers consist of materials relating to three generations of the Pierce family of Cornwall, principally Joshua Pierce (ca.1702-1794) and his son Seth Pierce (1742-1833), but also several of Joshua’s grandchildren.. Originally from Pembroke, Massachusetts, the Pierce family removed to Cornwall in 1748. Joshua Pierce and his descendants were particularly influential in community military and religious matters.
Scope and Content Note
Joshua Pierce’s deeds reveal the family’s vast property holdings first in eastern Massachusetts, and later in Cornwall. The Revolutionary War records of Seth Pierce deal primarily with the purchases of weapons and food, as well as troop movements in western Connecticut. The deeds of Seth Pierce show his steady accumulation of land in Cornwall during and after the war, especially in the Great Hollow. Seth Pierce’s receipts reveal transactions with individuals such as Ebenezer Sherwood, Hannah Griffis, Isaac Swift, Benjamin Conkling, Eleanor Johnson, Daniel Merritt, Isaac Talman, Josiah Sanford, Ethel North, Ozias Buell, and Dr. Ebenezer North. Seth Pierce’s influence in local military and religious matters is reflected in his accounts with both General Heman Swift and the First Ecclesiastical Society. The deeds of Seth Pierce’s son, “Major” Seth II, similarly illustrate a steady accumulation of land in Cornwall, especially from the Gold family in Cornwall Plains.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged generationally then chronologically within each generation.
The files are grouped into 4 series:
Joshua Pierce
Seth Pierce
Grandchildren of Joshua Pierce
Miscellaneous
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Deeds; military records; Receipts (financial records); Cornwall Historical Society; Pierce, Joshua (1702-1794); Pierce, Seth (1742-1833)
- Joshua Pierce
  - Deeds, 1725-1768 (Box 1, Folder 17-Jan)
  - Militia Appointment, 1758 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Seth Pierce
  - Revolutionary War, 1779-1783; , undated (Box 1, Folder 19-28)
  - Deeds, 1771-1814 (Box 1, Folder 29-42)
  - Receipts, 1783-1796 (Box 1, Folder 43-53)
  - Accounts, 1786-1811 (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
  - Tax Agreement with Matthew Patterson, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Letter from W. Chidester, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Complaint against trespassers from Kent, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Will, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Grandchildren of Joshua Pierce
  - Dwight W. Pierce Correspondence, 1846-1854 (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
  - Dwight W. Pierce, Description of Pangman Farm, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - John H. Pierce, Receipt from Daniel Boardman, Treasurer of the American Society for the Melioration of the Jews, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Joseph Pierce, Description of Inheritance from Silas Beers, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Joshua Pierce, Correspondence with William Bonney, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Joshua Pierce, Correspondence with D. Parker, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Joshua Pierce, Receipt from Josiah Hopkins, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Joshua Pierce, Fire Insurance Policy, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Seth Pierce, Deeds, 1844-1871 (Box 1, Folder 69-75)
  - Seth Pierce, Correspondence with L. Bierce, 1828-1831 (Box 1, Folder 76-77)
  - Seth Pierce, Correspondence with A. Beers, including a sample of black cloth from a surtout, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Miscellaneous
  - Creditor Agreement Regarding Jonathan Dibble Estate, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Note Detailing the Purchase of the Pierce Family Papers, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 80)